Register of the Ernest Schelling papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest Schelling papers
1867-1994
2012C39
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (9.6 linear feet)
The Ernest Schelling papers largely consist of printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, much of it relating to Schelling’s service as a major in the United States Army during World War I and as an assistant military attaché in Switzerland during and immediately after that war. The papers also contain materials pertaining to Schelling’s long career as a classical pianist and conductor, and especially to his friendship with the Polish musician and statesman, Ignace (Ignacy) Paderewski. There is some personal correspondence in the collection, as well as correspondence belonging to Lucie (Lucy) Schelling (Ernest Schelling’s first wife) and Helen “Peggy” Schelling (his second wife and widow).
Schelling, Ernest, 1876-1939.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012 from the family of Schelling's second wife, Helen "Peggy" Marshall, later Mrs. Helen Scholz, with incremental material received later.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Archival Materials note
Ernest Schelling collection, International Piano Archives, University of Maryland
Separated Materials
Orders, Decorations and Insignia, Military and Civil; With the History and Romance of Their Origin and a Full Description of Each, Robert Wyllie, 1921, given to Hoover Library.
Biographical Note
1876 July 26 Born, Belvedere, New Jersey
1888 Began studying piano with Ignace Paderewski
1917 Commissioned as major in the United States Army
1917-1919 Served as assistant military attaché, American Legation, Berne, Switzerland
1924-1939 Conductor, Young People's Concerts of the New York Philharmonic Symphonic Society
1936-1938 Music director, Baltimore Symphony
1939 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ernest Schelling papers largely consist of printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, much of it relating to Schelling’s service as a major in the United States Army during World War I and as an assistant military attaché in Switzerland during and immediately after that war. The World War I materials include copies of American government publications relating to military affairs, clippings, serial issues, and numerous photographs depicting soldiers of the American Expeditionary Forces in action in France and Germany. There are also copies of proclamations issued by the German military in occupied Belgium. In addition, the papers contain Schelling’s translation of one volume of the official German history of World War I. Official and personal correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and other materials relating to Schelling's service as an assistant military attaché can also be found in the Incremental Materials (Boxes 8-13).
Also included in the collection are materials pertaining to Schelling’s long career as a classical pianist and conductor, and especially to his friendship with the Polish musician and statesman, Ignace (Ignacy) Paderewski. There are photographs of Paderewski, including ones from his childhood, as well as programs relating to concert performances by Paderewski.
There is also some personal correspondence in the collection, as well as correspondence belonging to Lucie (Lucy) Schelling (Ernest Schelling’s first wife) and Helen “Peggy” Schelling (his second wife and widow). The collection also contains significant memorabilia, including various awards received by Schelling, as well as his World War I army uniform.
Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941.; United States. Army.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns.
- Biographical File, 1904-1937 (Box 1)
  - Address book, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Letters of appointment as major in the U.S. Army, 1918-1937 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Lists of awards and commissions, 1920-1937 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Passport and visas, 1904-1919 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Clippings relating to World War I and European politics, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Correspondence, 1916-1929 (Box 1)
  - Godson, W. F. H., 1927 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Riaño y Gayangos, Juan, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - University of Pennsylvania (Edward W. Mumford, Josiah H. Penniman), 1928-1929 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Declassified U.S. Government Publications, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Army War College, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 9-12)
  - U.S. State Department, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Leaflets from Germany, Poland, and Switzerland, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 1: 14)
- Photographs, 1867-1941 (Boxes 1-2)
  - 4 prints depicting Ernest Schelling in military uniform, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - 4 prints depicting Ernest Schelling and Allied military attachés in Berne, Switzerland, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - 1 print depicting Ernest Schelling and Allied military attachés in Berne, Switzerland, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - 1 print depicting Ernest Schelling and Ignace (Ignacy) Paderewski at ceremony when Schelling was awarded the Distinguished Service Medal, 1923 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - 1 print depicting Ernest Schelling, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - 6 prints depicting Ernest Schelling and Ignace Paderewski, 1935 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - 7 reproductions depicting Ignace Paderewski and his family, 1867-1875 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1 print and 2 reproductions depicting Ignace Paderewski, 1890-1905 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 11 prints depicting Ignace Paderewski and his family, 1890-1905 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1 print depicting an artist's sketch of Ignace Paderewski, 1891 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1 print and 1 reproduction depicting Ignace Paderewski, 1900 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 3 prints and 1 reproduction depicting Ignace Paderewski, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - 1 print depicting a sculpture of Ignace Paderewski, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - 1 print depicting a portrait of Ignace Paderewski, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - 2 prints depicting Ignace Paderewski, 1935 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - 6 prints depicting Ignace Paderewski, 1935-1940 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - 3 prints depicting Ignace Paderewski and Eleanor Roosevelt, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - 1 print depicting Alfred Paderewski, 1899 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - 1 signed print depicting Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt, 1936 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - 30 prints of U.S. Army Signal Corps photographs depicting American soliders during World War I, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - 29 prints of U.S. Army Signal Corps photographs depicting American soldiers during World War I, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - 2 prints of U.S. Army Signal Corps photographs depicting women volunteers in France, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - 12 prints of U.S. Army Signal Corps photographs depicting Allied military airplanes, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - 3 prints depicting Lieutenant Fletcher, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - 34 prints depicting soldiers of the Swiss army, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - 1 print depicting a collection of weapons and armor belonging to Ernest Schelling, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 20)
- Proclamations issued by the German military in occupied Belgium, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Programs relating to concert recitals by Ignace Paderewski, 1915-1942 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Translation by Ernest Schelling of official history of the German army in World War I, Der Weltkrieg 1914 bis 1918, volume II, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 3-6)
- Helen "Peggy" Schelling correspondence file, 1940-1994 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- Lucie (Lucy) Schelling correspondence file, 1924 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Oversize Materials, 1914-1936 (Boxes 4-6)
  - Blueprints and description of German trenches, 1915 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Certificates, 1919-1936 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Ordre National de la Légion d’Honneur, 1919
    - Order Odrodzenia Polski, Polonia Restituta, 1925
    - Ordre du Saint-Sépulcre Orthodoxe, 1929
    - Distinguished Service Medal, 1934
    - Credentials as delegate to International Theater Congress, 1936
  - Letter of appointment from the U.S. Army, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Maps of France, Germany, and the United States, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Photograph depicting Ernest Schelling at a military ceremony, 1921 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Print of President Taft, 1913 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes an inscription by Taft: "For Mr. Ernest Schelling with grateful appreciation of the wonderful music drawn from the piano he gave us at the White House February 7th 1913."
  - Print of portrait of Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph von Schelling (German philosopher), undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Poster insert from German newspaper, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Proclamations issued by the German army in Belgium and France, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Serial issues, 1914-1919
    - Basler Nachrichten, 1917 December 19 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Berliner Ilustrirte Zeitung, 1917 November 25
    - Der Bund, 1918 November 1-December 19
    - L’Écho de Grèce, 1918 May 23
    - La Feuille, 1918 January 21-April 30
    - Frankfurter Zeitung, 1914 September 15
    - Gazette de Laussanne, 1914 December 13
    - Illustrirte Zeitung, 1917 December 13
    - Impartial Suisse, 1918 December 21-1919 January 4
    - Der Kommunist, 1919 April (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - Lustigen Blätter, No. 37, 1914
    - Nachrichtenblatt für Balten, 1919 March 26-April 3
    - La Nation, 1918 February 24-March 9
    - Neue Zeitung, 1919 February 22
    - Neue Zürcher Zeitung, 1917 December 16
    - Neuer Freier Aargauer, 1917 December 28
    - Schweizer Illustrierte Zeitung, 1918 March 30
    - Stimmen aus dem Osten, 1919 March 19-26
    - La Suisse, 1918 November 9 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Über Land und Meer, No. 49, 1914
    - Der Welt Spiegel, 1914 September 13
    - Die wirtschaftliche Demobilmachung, 1919 February 8-9
    - Die Woche, 1914 September 12
  - Memorabilia, 1918-1934
    - Framed display of medals awarded to Ernest Schelling, 1919-1934 (Box 5)
      Includes the Ordre National de la Légion d’honneur; the Order Odrodzenia Polski, Polonia Restituta; the Ordre du Saint-Sépulcre Orthodoxe; and the Distinguished Service Medal.
    - U.S. Army cap worn by Ernest Schelling, 1918 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Army jacket worn by Ernest Schelling, 1918 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Army patches, 1918-1920 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Army pins and insignia, 1918-1920 (Box 6)
    - Légion d'Honneur (Legion of Honor) medal and case, 1918 (Box 6)
    - Order of Polonia Restituta case, undated (Box 6)
    - Pair of stirrups, 1918 (Box 6)
- Printed Matter, 1911-1928 (Box 7)
  - Brochures relating to Ignace Paderewski, 1916-1928 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Monographs, 1911-1928
    - Infantry Drill Regulations, United States Army, 1911 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Regulations of the Army of the United States, 1917 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Géographie des principales puissances du monde, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Gore, James Howard, American Legionnaires of France, 1920 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - To Ignace Paderewski, Artist, Patriot, Humanitarian, 1928
  - Pamphlets relating to American and German military policy, 1917
    - General, 1917 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - Army War College, 1917 (Box-folder 7: 8)
- Incremental Materials, 1899-1991 (Boxes 8-13)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, newspaper clippings, ephemera, address books, notebooks, passports, and photographs largely relating to Schelling's time as an assistant military attaché in Switzerland after World War I and his friendship with Ignace Paderewski, arranged alphabetically by subject or physical form. See "Key to military file" (Box 8, folder 1) for more information about the organization of the materials.
  - Key to military file, undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Handwritten and typed notes provided by a relative of Schelling's, detailing the organization of Schelling's papers. There is an item-level index indicating which items were found together under Schelling's original organizational scheme and then a cross-reference indicating which descriptive headings the items were put under. These latter headings are what were used as the folder titles for the Military file of the Incremental Materials, and any additional notes were added as Scope and Content notes, in quotation marks.
  - Military file, 1912-1963
    - Accident, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - Agents, 1918-1919, undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - Biographical material, 1917-1939 (Box-folder 8: 4)
      Includes military identity cards, diplomatic passes and passports, certificates, travel documents, and summaries of Schelling's military activities/rankings and decorations.
    - Bolshevism, 1918-1919, undated (Box-folder 8: 5-6)
    - Codes, undated (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Correspondence
      - Official, 1914-1934 (Box-folder 8: 8-9, Box-folder 9: 1)
        From folders labeled "Major Schelling - Official," "Major Schelling - Official - Personal," and "Poland." Largely consists of correspondence and orders directly relating to Schelling's military duties.
      - Unofficial, 1912-1935 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
        From folder labeled "Military - Unofficial letters to Major Schelling." Largely consists of correspondence received by Schelling during his military career or from military colleagues unrelated to his duties or of a more personal nature.
    - General information on intelligence, 1917-1924, 1954 (Box-folder 9: 4-5)
    - Inventions, 1914, 1918 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - Lists, 1919, undated (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
      "Lists of officials - Berne; official address book; M.A. ball - June 26, 1919."
    - Maps, undated (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - Military Intelligence Reserve, 1920-1939 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - Military Intelligence resumé, 1923, undated (Box-folder 10: 5)
      "Report of military attaché's office."
    - Military Order of the World War, 1926-1938 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916-1923, 1938, 1963 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - Photographs of friends and colleagues, 1919-1920, undated (Box-folder 10: 8)
      Original folder included handwritten notation: "See article, Musical Courier, April 14, 1921."
    - Reports re Austria, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 9)
      "1 by Major Schelling."
    - Reports re Bulgaria and Turkey, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - Reports re France, 1914, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - Reports re Germany, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 10: 12, Box-folder 11: 1)
      "(?) several by Major Schelling."
    - Reports re grippe, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Reports re Poland, Czechoslovakia, Ukraine, Lithuania, 1918, undated (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - Reports re prisoners, 1914-1919 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - Reports re Russia, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Reports re Switzerland, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      "At least 6 by Major Schelling."
    - Reports re United States, 1917-1921 (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - Reserve Officers Association, 1920-1938 (Box-folder 11: 8)
      "Includes 61st Cavalry Division."
  - Personal file, 1899-1991
    - Address books and notebooks, undated (Box-folder 11: 9-10)
    - Paderewski, Ignace (Ignacy), 1899-1965
      - Correspondence
        - Between the Schellings (Ernest, Lucie, Helen) and Paderewski/Paderewska, 1899-1941 (Box-folder 12: 1-4)
          Letters, notes, cables, telegrams, and postcards. With two exceptions, the postcards (1902-1904) are addressed to Madame [Helena] Paderewska from Ernest Schelling. The other two are addressed to Madame Jaszowska, Paderewska's aunt.
        - Between Ernest Schelling and others re Paderewski
          - General, 1899-1939 (Box-folder 12: 5)
          - Re "Memoirs" (Mary Lawton book), 1929, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 12: 6)
          - Re newspaper articles, 1915-1934 (Box-folder 12: 7)
            The majority of the material relates to a Saturday Evening Post article, 7 April 1934, which disparaged Paderewski.
          - Re Paderewski week (17-23 January 1937) and proposed Paderewski Fund, 1936-1940 (Box-folder 12: 8)
          - Re Paso Robles ranch, 1921, undated (Box-folder 12: 9)
          - Strakacz, Sylwin, 1931-1939 (Box-folder 12: 10)
        - Between Helen "Peggy" Schelling and others re Paderewski, 1940-1965 (Box-folder 12: 11)
        - Between Lucie (Lucy) Schelling and others re Paderewski, 1920-1934 (Box-folder 12: 12)
          Includes RSVPs (acceptances and regrets) to 20 February 1921 reception for Paderewski at the Colony Club.
      - Funeral, 1941, 1946, undated (Box-folder 13: 1)
        Includes handwritten notes regarding annoucement of funeral services at Arlington National Cemetery in 1941, invitation to a fifth anniversary mass in 1946, and a list of friends.
      - Miscellaneous, 1901-1942, undated (Box-folder 13: 2)
        Notes, receipts, press release, and summaries of information relating to Paderewski, Schelling, and other topics.
      - Photographs, 1930s, undated (Box-folder 13: 3)
        Largely photographs of Paderewski and Schelling, but some group shots of Paderewski in domestic setting with others are included as well. See also: Boxes 1-2.
      - Tributes (by Schelling), 1915-1940, undated (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Photographs of Schelling (4 prints), undated (Box-folder 13: 5)
      See also: Boxes 1-2.
    - Schelling, Helen "Peggy,", 1939-1991 (Box-folder 13: 6)
      Correspondence, notes, printed matter, press release, and program relating to Schelling and his legacy, the military, and Paderewski, received or collected by Schelling's second wife, Helen.
    - Schelling, Lucie (Lucy), 1914-1938 (Box-folder 13: 7-8)
      Correspondence, notes, and passports of Schelling's first wife, Lucie, as well as materials relating to her death and funeral.
    - Miscellaneous, 1930, 1960, undated (Box-folder 13: 9)
      Consists of a cartoon, undated; a typescript draft of a concert program, undated; a zeppelin ticket, 1930; and a flyer for a piano recital by Claudette Sorel, 1960.
    - Printed matter, 1919-1949 (Box-folder 13: 10-11)
      - Aubert, Maître, Bolshevism's Terrible Record: An Indictment, issued under the auspices of the Entente Internationale contre le IIIe Internationale, 1924
      - Flynn, John T., The Road Ahead: America's Creeping Revolution, 1949
      - Herzig & McLean, Inc., General Pershing's Story of the American Army in France, 1919
        Reprints General Pershing's 20 November 1918 report to the Secretary of War, as well as some World War I poetry.
      - Novik, Dmitri, Théodore Aubert et Son Oeuvre: Le Mouvement International Contre le Bolchévisme, édition des Amis de l'Entente Internationale contre la IIIe Internationale, 1932
      - Otto Ulbrich Co., Catalogue of United States Martial Short Arms, 1939
    - Tributes, 1940, 1956 (Box-folder 13: 12)
      Related to Schelling's support of music and his fellow musicians, particularly through the Musicians Emergency Fund.
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1918, 1920, undated (Box 13)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 January release of records, 1918, 1920, undated (Box-folder 13: 13)
    Consists of documents relating to Schelling's work as an assistant military attaché in Berne, Switzerland after World War I:
    "Synposis of Cables Between the American Minister, Berne, Switzerland, and the State Department, with Reference to McN.," undated.
    Memorandum re the Czech delegation in Switzerland, undated.
    Letter from Schelling to Colonel Van Deman, Chielf Intelligence Section, War College, Washington D.C., 2 March 1918.
    "The Situation in Germany: An Interview with a German Officer in the Würtemberg Infantry (Engineer Corps), a Mining Engineer," 25 May 1920.